<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thunder from heaven against the back-sliders and apostates of the times. In some meditations on the 24 chapter of Isaiah. / By W.A.</title>
            <author>Aspinwall, William, fl. 1648-1662.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1655</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 89 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75734</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A4009</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E831_26</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207507</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866552</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866552</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118828</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75734)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118828)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 126:E831[26])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Thunder from heaven against the back-sliders and apostates of the times. In some meditations on the 24 chapter of Isaiah. / By W.A.</title>
                  <author>Aspinwall, William, fl. 1648-1662.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[7], 39 [i.e. 32], [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Livewell Chapman, and are to be sold at the Crown in Popes-head-alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1655.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>W. A. = William Aspinwall.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E⁴.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aprill. 14".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Isaiah, XXIV --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118828:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THUNDER From HEAVEN Againſt the BACK-SLIDERS and APOSTATES Of the TIMES. In ſome Meditations on the 24 Chapter of <hi>Iſaiah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>W. A.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Amos. 3. 8.</bibl> The Lyon hath roared, who will not feare? The Lord hath ſpoken, who can but Propheſie?</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Jer. 23. 8.</bibl> Then I ſaid, I wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ake mention of him, nor ſpeak any more in his nam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> word was in mine heart as a burning fire ſhut up <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>; and I was weary with forbearing, and I could <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Livewell Chapman,</hi> and are to be ſold at the Crown in Popes-head-alley, 1655,</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:118828:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:118828:2"/>
            <head>THE AUTHOR TO THE Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE words of</hi> Jehovah <hi>are pure words, as ſilver tryed in a furnace of earth, puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied ſeven times,</hi> Pſal. 12. 6. They are alſo precious, and <hi>more to be deſired then gold, yea then much fine gold,</hi> Pſal. 19. 10. And as it's with purified ſilver or gold, each grain is
<pb facs="tcp:118828:3"/> precious, and hath its weight: ſo is it with the word of God. Each word, ſyllable, and letter, yea each vowel and accent hath its worth and weight; as in part I have ſhewed, in a little brief explication of the ſeventh of <hi>Daniel.</hi> Which poor labour hath received ſome ſquint blows, that are not worthy the anſwer; in as much as they contain more words then weight, and leave too much up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on humane authority (though none of them would be thought ſo to do) and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which, their ſtrength would faile; as hereafter I may poſſibly manifeſt in ſome meditations upon the eighth of <hi>Daniel,</hi> a place very much miſtaken by ſome good men, for want of due attendance to Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture-language. And now I do here pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent thee with ſome meditations upon the twenty fourth of <hi>Iſaiah;</hi> in which Chapter are contained many ſad predictions of ſore calamities to befal a Land, to which the Prophet gives no name. Wherefore I have took occaſion, at vacant hours, to weigh the words and circumſtances in the text, for my own private help, to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand
<pb facs="tcp:118828:3"/> the Counſel of God therein. And per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving many things therein (if duly attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) might be both publikely and privately uſeful; I durſt not conceal it within my own breſt, leſt I ſhould incur the guilt of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfulneſs, if having but one poor Talent, I ſhould go &amp; hide it in a napkin. And though the Prophet apply it not to any particular Land by name, neither dare I preſume to make particular application thereof (wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a clear word for my warrant) yet for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch as Scriptures may be Analogically applyed, and ſo become uſeful to all ſuccee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding times, nations, and perſons; I thought it would not be unuſeful to explicate the words of this Propheſie, according to the property of the language wherein they are written, as Maſter <hi>Ainſworth</hi> hath done upon the books of <hi>Moſes</hi> and other Scriptures. That ſo every one that reads may conſider how far they are, or may be concerned therein, and make a profitable uſe thereof for themſelves. For this let me ſay to thee, whoſoever thou art, If thou fall under the guilt of theſe ſins of Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,
<pb facs="tcp:118828:4"/> hypocriſie, and Covenant-breaking, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> mentioned in this Chapter; be aſſured, God hath reſerved FEAR, or a PIT, or a SNARE for thee, to wit, variety of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of ſuch a nature, to humble thee withall. But beware of making miſ-ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications of what the Prophet ſpeaketh, and is here briefly unfolded, leſt theſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils be thy portion. And though many who minde not the things of God and his threatnings, will much leſs minde any thing I have ſaid in this little Treatiſe; yet the poor flock of Chriſt (for whoſe ſake I have chiefly penned it) will incline their ears and liſten: and if they perceive the voice of Chriſt breathing therein, they will ſoon diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern it, from the voice of a ſtranger. When they hear the Lyon of the tribe of <hi>Judah</hi> roar, they will tremble: and when he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites them with an amiable compellation (as indeed he doth, <hi>Iſa. 26. 10.) Come my people,</hi> they will attend his voice, and <hi>enter into their chambers,</hi> and draw neer to God, and wreſtle with him as <hi>Jacob</hi> did, for mercy in behalf of themſelves, and of the land where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb facs="tcp:118828:4"/> they live, that the anger of the Lord may be turned away from them. Read therefore and conſider, and let not the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurity and tenuity of the Author make thee to ſlight it, but conſider the Majeſty and Authority of the word of the Lord, and receive that, and nothing but what agrees thereunto. As touching the particular time and ſeaſon, when the words of this propheſie are to be accompliſhed, the text doth not ſpeak to it, nor dare I; onely this is evident, that all theſe ſad predictions ſhall receive their accompliſhment, at or a little before the glorious raign of Chriſt Jeſus, before his ancient people the Jews. Which, as I have elſwhere obſerved, will not be above nineteen yeers yet to come: I mean, the firſt beginning of the Jews re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn. Wait therefore and ſtand, <hi>having your loins girt. For he that will come, will come, and will not tarry.</hi>
            </p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Prae-monitus prae-munitus.</q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:118828:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118828:5"/>
            <head>A Premonition of ſundry ſad Calamities yet to come.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Grounded upon an Explication of the 24 Chapter of Iſaiah.</head>
               <p n="1">1 <hi>BEhold, Jehovah maketh the land empty, and maketh it waſte, and perverteth the face thereof and ſcattereth abroad the inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants thereof.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>And it ſhall be, as with the people, ſo with the Prieſt, as with the ſervant, ſo with his maſter, as with the hand-maid ſo with her miſtreſſe: as with the buyer ſo with the ſeller, as with the lender ſo with the borrower, as with the taker upon uſury, ſo with the lender up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon uſury.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3 <hi>The land ſhall be utterly emptied, and ſhall be utterly ſpoiled: for Jehovah hath ſpoken this word.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4 <hi>The land mourneth fadeth, the world languiſheth fadeth: the HIGH ONE of the people of the land do languiſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5 <hi>The land is defiled under the inhabitants thereof: for they have tranſgreſſed the Law, changed the Statute, and broken the everlaſting Covenant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6 <hi>Therefore the curſe hath conſumed the land, and they that dwel therein are guilty: therefore the inhabitants of the land are inraged, and the poor little man left.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7 <hi>The new wine mourneth, the vine languiſheth: all the merry hearted do ſigh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8 <hi>The mirth of tabrets ceaſeth, the noyſe of them that rejoyce is left off, the joy of the harp ceaſeth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">9 <hi>They ſhal not drink wine with a ſong: ſtrong wine ſhal be bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to the drinkers thereof.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">10 <hi>The Citie</hi> Tohu <hi>is broken: every houſe is ſhut up from going in.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="11">11 <hi>There is crying for wine in the ſtreets: all joy is darkened, the mirth of the land is gone.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="12">12 <hi>In this citie is left aſtoniſhment, and the gate is ſmitten with deſtruction.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="13">13 <hi>When thus it ſhal be in the midſt of this land, among the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: as it were the ſhaking of an Olive tree, as the gleaning of grapes when the vintage is done.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="14">
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:118828:6"/>14 <hi>Theſe ſhal lift up their voyce, they ſhal ſing in the majeſty of Jehovah, they ſhal ſhout aloud for joy from the ſea.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="15">15 <hi>Wherefore with <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RIM glorifie ye Jehovah in the Iſles of the ſea: the name of Jehovah the God of Iſrael.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="16">16 <hi>From the wing of this land we have heard ſongs, glory to the righteous, but I ſaid, my leanneſſe, my leanneſſe, wo unto me: the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous dealers have dealt treacherouſly, yea the treacherous dealers have dealt very treacherouſly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="17">17 <hi>FEAR, and the PIT, and she SNARE: upon thee, O in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of that land.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="18">18 <hi>And it ſhal come to paſſe, he that flies from the noyſe of the FEAR, ſhall fall into the PIT, and he that aſcends out of the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt of the PIT, ſhall be taken in the SNARE: for the windows from the MOST HIGH are opened, and the foundations of the land do ſhake.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="19">19 <hi>The land is ſore bruiſed: the land is utterly broken, the land is quite diſplaced.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="20">20 <hi>The land ſhal reel to and fro like a drunkard, and ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved like a cottage: for the tranſgreſſion thereof ſhal be heavy upon it, and it ſhall fall, and never riſe any more.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="21">21 <hi>And it ſhal come to paſſe in that very day, Jehovah will pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the</hi> Militia <hi>of that HIGH ONE, with that HIGH ONE, and the Kings of the earth, upon the earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="22">22 <hi>And they ſhall be gathered together with a gathering, a priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner for the dungeon: and very many dayes ſhal they be puniſhed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="23">23 <hi>Then the Moon ſhall be confounded, and the Sun aſhamed: for the LORD OF HOSTS ſhal reign in mount Zyon, and in Jeruſalem, and before his Ancients gloriouſly.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>THis Chapter, and the three ſubſequent Chapters, are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly calcualted for this very Age wherein we live, as in the enſuing Diſcourſe will more fully appear. But this 24 chapter doth in a ſpeciall manner contain the ſad and inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>icable calamities that will befall the unbeleeving world, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the end of their worldly governments, a little before the glorious coming of the kingdom of our Lord Jeſus, which in the later end of the fourth Monarchy will be ſligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and yet dreaded; inſomuch that men will be troubled to hear of it, as ſometime <hi>Herod</hi> was, and the carnal Church alſo,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:118828:6"/> when it was reported that this King <hi>Jeſus</hi> was born, <hi>Mat.</hi> 2. 3. But let men of earthly ſpirits (who mind more the Mammon of this world, and the dignities thereof, then the coming of Chriſts kingdom, which he taught his diſciples to pray for,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 6. 10) I ſay, let them deem as they pleaſe, and make a ſcoff at it, as <hi>Peter</hi> tells us they will, 2 <hi>Pet. 3. 3. in the later end of dayss, ſaying, Where is the promiſe of his coming?</hi> (which is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of this very age wherin we live) yet let ſuch know, that for all this <hi>God will bring them to judgement, Eccleſ.</hi> 11. 9. And the day of Chriſts coming (which now they ſlight) wil be to them as a thief in the night, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5. 2. And theſe mockers, of what rank ſoever, ſhal cry to the mountains and to the rocks, to fall upon them, and cover them from the wrath of the Lamb, and him that ſits upon the Throne (whom now they perſecute in his poore members) <hi>Rev.</hi> 6. from v. 12. to the end of the chapter. Therefore <hi>be wiſe O ye Kings, be inſtructed O yee Judges of the earth, ſerve the Lord with fear and rejoyce with trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling. Kiſs the Son leſt he be angry, and ye periſh from the way, when his wrath is kindled but a little.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now ere I come to the words of the explication of this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie, let me premiſe theſe three things to be conſidered.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That there is no prediction of judgement, nor promiſe of mercy in Scripture, but it relates to ſome particular thing, perſon, nation or time; or elſe generally to all things, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, nations, and times, under the ſame or the like condition.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That whatſoever is particularly applied to ſome parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular thing, perſon, nation, or time, may be applied Analogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally and by way of proportion, unto any other things, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, nations and times, upon the ſame or the like terms.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That particular judgements threatned in caſe of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, may be obviated, and prevented in whole or in part: and ſo alſo mercies in caſe of apoſtaſie and backſliding.</p>
               <p>Theſe things premiſed, I ſhall briefly come to a particular diſquiſition of this Propheſie, which nameth no particular perſon, nation, or time, and explicate as I go along, what is moſt obſtruce, without juſt offence to any; ſubmitting what I ſhall hold forth to the judgement of thoſe who are able to judge of ſpirituall things, and willing to weigh all things in the ballance of the Sanctuary.</p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:118828:7"/>
               <p>In this Propheſie of <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> as in other of the Prophets, you may obſerve particular Propheſies againſt particular coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries. As againſt <hi>Babylon</hi> in the 13, 14. 21. and 47. chapters; Againſt <hi>Moab</hi> in the 15, and 16. chapters; againſt <hi>Damaſcus</hi> in the 17. chapter; againſt <hi>Ethiopia</hi> in the 18 chapter, againſt <hi>Egypt</hi> in the 19 chapter, and againſt both of them in the 20 chapter; againſt <hi>Edom</hi> and <hi>Arabia</hi> in the 21 chapter; againſt <hi>Ephraim</hi> in the 28 chap. againſt <hi>Judah</hi> &amp; <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> in the 29 &amp; 30 &amp; 31 chapters; againſt the Idols of <hi>Babell</hi> chapter 46. All which may be applyed by way of proportion againſt any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Idols, Perſons, Nations, and Places in any other age, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſame, or the like termes.</p>
               <p>This 24 chapter is a Propheſie againſt a particular Land or Nation (as hereafter will more clearly appeare) but giveth no name to it. And probably it may be thought that the Land whereof he ſpeaks, was not at that time peopled, nor ſubjected to Government, and therefore not named. If any ſhould ſuppoſe it to relate to <hi>Tyrus,</hi> of which mention is made in the chapter foregoing; I conceive it cannot be ſo for theſe Reaſons.</p>
               <p>1. The Prophet in the cloſe of the foregoing chapter fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tells the reſtauration and flouriſhing ſtate of <hi>Tyrus</hi> after her vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitation, and therefore what he ſpeaks of this Land, cannot well be underſtood of <hi>Tyre.</hi> 2ly. The Land here ſpoken of is an Iſland or Iſlands environed with Sea, as appeares from the 14 and 15 verſes: whereas <hi>Tyrus</hi> is an haven town upon the main Continent. 3ly. The judgement denounced againſt <hi>Tyrus</hi> was long ſince executed, whereas the judgements here threatned to befall this Land, ſhall be in the latter dayes not long before the Converſion of the Jewes, and the coming of the glorious Kingdome of our Lord Jeſus: wherefore I take it to be a Propheſie of, or concerning ſome particular Land or Iſlands in theſe latter times.</p>
               <p>But ere I come to a particular examination of the words in their order, I ſhall give you this brief Analyſis of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets method in this chapter. Firſt he ſhews the various changes and alterations of Government in that Land, in the ſoure firſt verſes. 2ly. The ground and cauſe thereof, to wit, their hypocriſie and apoſtacie, in the 5 verſe. 3ly. The ſad
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:118828:7"/> conſequents both of their ſin and of thoſe alterations, from the 5 verſe to the end of the 12. 4ly. Gods reſervation of a remnant which ſhall glorifie him in thoſe Iſlands, ver. 13, 14, 15, and part of the 16. 5ly. The treachery of the inſtrumens who were beſtruſted by the Nation, and were active in all theſe changes, verſe 16, 17, 18. 6ly. The diſſolution of their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall formes of Government, verſe 19, 20. 7ly. The pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of the Inſtruments, verſe 21. together with the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of the Kings of the neighbouring Nations, verſe 21, 22. And laſtly the principal Efficient of all theſe mutations, Jehovah the Lord of Hoſts; and the end he aimed at, to wit, the ſetting up of his Sons Kingdome in all the Nations, but more eſpecially amongſt his Ancient people, verſe 23.</p>
               <p>Ver. 1. <hi>Behold.</hi>] This word of attention is prefixed to quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> up the hearts of Gods people to a ſerious attention of what the Prophet is about to deliver, and to a deligent ſearch after the minde and counſell of God therein. And it implies, that there is ſomething more then ordinary to be treated of, ſome remarkable occurrence of Providence, not elſwhere tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched by him. Wherefore the Propheſie being for a long time then to come, and vailed with many Metaphors, and the name of the Land or Iſlands concealed; the Spirit of God thought it meet to give this note of attention, leaſt otherwiſe his Councell therein ſhould not be perceived.</p>
               <p>Ver. 1. <hi>Jehovah emptieth the Land.</hi>] The word wich is tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated <hi>emptieth,</hi> and the other word tranſlated <hi>maketh it waſte,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> are both Participles of the preſent tenſe, as if he ſhould ſay, <hi>the Lord is emptying and making it waſte.</hi> Which holds forth to us two preparatory Acts of God, making way for the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing changes of Government in that Land, or in thoſe Iſlands. And when the Prophet ſaith <hi>Jehovah did empty the Land</hi> &amp;c. It implies Gods approbation of it, and that he had a deſigne of his own in hand whilſt he is about this work, and what that deſigne was, will be ſpoken of hereafter. <hi>Emptieth.</hi>]<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> The word properly ſignifies ſuch an emptying, as when one emptieth a narrow mouthed bottle, which they call <hi>Bakbuk,</hi> from the bubling noiſe it maketh in emptying. So that the word imports ſome murmure of the people, when God thus begins to empty the Repreſentative of the Land; ſome ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:118828:8"/> ſome diſapproving the Action. <hi>The Land.</hi>] The<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> word ſignifies Earth or Land; And ſometimes is put for the whole dry land or habitable part of the world, as <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. 10.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> and ſo it may be derived from a word that ſignifies, to run up and down about their occaſions and negotiations. Or elſe it is put for ſome particular Region or Country and the Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction thereof, as its moſt uſuall, and ſo it may be derived of a word that ſignifies a voluntary choiſe, becauſe men vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarily<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> ſubject themſelves to ſuch a Government. And in that ſence I take it here in this Propheſie: Underſtanding the Repreſentative of the land to be put Synechdochically for the whole land. Now for as much as the Prophet hath given no name to this land, neither ſhall I apply it to any one land or other peculiarly, ſaving only by way of proportion in the cloſe of this diſcourſe.</p>
               <p>Yet for the better opening and applying of this Propheſie let me adde theſe few conſiderations more touching this land. Firſt that it cannot principally be meant of any land or coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try upon the main Continent, becauſe it is called Iſlands of the Sea, ver. 15. And Iſlands of the Sea are diſtinguiſhed from inland Countries, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 11. 11. Such as were <hi>Aſſyria, Egypt, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throſh, Guſh, Elam, Shinar,</hi> and <hi>Hamath.</hi> All which Countries in Scripture phraſe are called Iſlands, as <hi>Iſa.</hi> 20. 6. But then they are called Iſlands ſimply, as in the place next foremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, or elſe Iſlands of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> as <hi>Gen. 10. 5. Zeph.</hi> 2. 11. Not Iſlands of the Sea, as in this place. Secondly, It is ſpoken of ſuch a land Government as extends it ſelfe to more Iſlands then one, as will be ſhewed more at large in the 15 ver. of this chapter. Thirdly, It is ſuch a land as aboundeth with much Heavenly light, as will be ſhewed upon the 15 ver. aforementioned. Fourthly, It is ſuch a Country as paſſeth under various and ſudden changes of Government, expreſſed by ſundry Metaphoricall phraſes, as will be opened, ver. 17. And laſtly it is ſuch a Land as hath one moſt <hi>High-one,</hi> who hath the Command of the <hi>Militia,</hi> and is inſtrumenticall in thoſe alterations of Government: which may ſuffice to give ſome light what the Prophet means by this land, ſo far as the circumſtances in the text doe lead us.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And maketh it waſte.</hi>] The word <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Significat diſſipare et effiingere quodclauſum et munitam erat, ut om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium injuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is patet.</hi> Merc. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Significat</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Buxtorf.</note> here uſed imports ſuch
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:118828:8"/> an act as breaketh down or infringeth the priviledges and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munities of the peoples Repreſentative, and thereby expoſeth them to injury and waſte: as will appear in the two enſuing Acts, which I call perfecting Acts. <hi>He perverteth the face thereof.</hi>] The word tranſlated <hi>perverteth</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> doth ſignify to winde and turne a thing about ſecretly, but ſtrongly. Which argues that the liberties being once infringed there will be ſome inſtrument or other which will by power and policy turne about the face of the Government. Or to ſpeak in ſouldiers language, will make them face about: and having thus done, he doth at length <hi>Scatter them abroad:</hi> which is the fourth Act; and theſe two laſt Acts are put forth by a power Paramount to the Repreſentative of the land. Theſe I call per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>infecting acts, becauſ the power that formerly was reſident the Repreſentative of the land, upon their diſſollution and ſcatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, devolves into the hand of that power that diſſolved them</p>
               <p>Hitherto God owns the actions as approvable in his ſight, ſobeit the power ſpoken of, and the inſtruments improved by him, do with ſimplicity and integrity carry on Gods deſign for ſetting up the kingdome of his Son in that land, ſeeking the publick peace and tranquility of the State, without any ſquint looks or ſecret deſigns to advance their own private intereſts. For now the nation ſtands in ſuch a poſture as ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders it capable of new forming, and ſetling upon a firm Baſis, under the ſubjection and protection of that bleſſed and onely <hi>Potentate</hi> the Lord Jeſus, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. 15. which would have been the happines of that nation. But here alas begins the woe and miſery of that poor land (through the treachery of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments) which the Prophet ſo ſadly laments in the 16 verſe of this chapter: For they having broken the everlaſting cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of profeſſed ſubjection to the Lord Jeſus onely, he now ſubjects the nation unto that moſt High One of the people, ſpoken of in the 4. verſe; and ſo they are taken in the ſame ſnare from which they fled under the terror of tyranny of the firſt Government, and might have been ſafe under the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond form of Government, of which more will we ſpoken hereafter in its proper place.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 2. In this verſe follows a perfect and reall levelling of all ranks and eſtates unto the power of that <hi>High One</hi> of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:118828:9"/> the people. Wherefore the Prophet ſaith, <hi>It ſhal be, as with the people, ſo with the Prieſt, as with the ſervant, ſo with his maſter, &amp;c.</hi> God will levell the Clergy, (as they are called) and the L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ity, and all ranks and qualities of men (not in their eſtates and proprieties) but he will levell them to judgement, none of them ſhal eſcape it; but as they have been all ſharers in ſin, and have all broken the everlaſting covenant, ſo they ſhal all be ſharers in the puniſhment thereof: For that is the true mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the phraſe, <hi>Like People, like Prieſt,</hi> as appears in <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4. 9. where the like expreſsions are uſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 3. Things thus ſtanding in that land, it ſeemes there will be an aſſembly of a ſecond Repreſentative by that moſt <hi>High one</hi> of the people, but of ſhort continuance; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſaith, <hi>in emptying they ſhall be emptied,</hi>] or as our tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation renders it (and not unfitly) the land ſhall be utterly emptied, and ſuddenly, all at once, not by degrees and ſteps, as the former was, but there ſhall be a ſpeedy diſpatch of this;<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> yet with a bubling noiſe and murmure of the people, as the word imports: ſome ſaying it is well done, others otherwiſe: This breach, or diſſolution, will be worſe reſented then the former, wherewith men ſeemed contented, or at leaſt ſhewed no diſcontent. And thus you have a ſhort end of the ſecond Repreſentative, after which followes a third; of which it is ſaid, <hi>it ſhall be utterly ſpoyled.</hi>] The word here uſed may be<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> derived either from a word <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> that ſignifies to abaſe &amp; render a thing contemptible, or it may be derived from another word that ſignifies to make a prey <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> or ſpoil of them, as ſouldiers do in war: and if you take it in this latter ſence, it argues the exerciſe of a Military power to overcome them, and bind them to conditions, unſuitable to their former ancient cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes, which renders them deſpicable and abaſeth them, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the former derivation of the word; For theſe two Roots have a neer affinity one with the other. Thus have you a metaphoricall repreſentation of the various changes of the Government in that land. And the certainty of all thoſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents is expreſſed in the next words, <hi>For Jehovah hath ſpoken this word.</hi>] God that cannot lie, and God that gives <hi>Being</hi> to all things hath ſpoken it: it is an irrevocable word. But as touching the conſequences of all theſe mutations and altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:118828:9"/> mentioned from the ſixth verſe and ſo forward, God hath not affixed this word of ratification thereunto, but leaves a room for repentance, that the judgments may be removed, either in whole, or in part, whereof more will be ſaid in the cloſe of this Diſcourſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Verſe 4. The land mourneth fadeth.</hi>] By <hi>land,</hi> as I ſaid before, I underſtand the Repreſentative of the land, part being put for the whole by a Synechdoche. <hi>It mourneth fadeth.</hi> The word tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>fadeth,</hi> doth ſignifie ſuch a fading as happens to leaves or flowers, or fruits when they have loſt their moiſture, and begin to wither, and at length fall from their trees. Which doth imply the drying up of the power of the lands Repreſentative, which kept them freſh &amp; flouriſhing; &amp; their mourning expreſſeth their unwillingneſs thus to be bereaved of their ancient liberties. So unpleaſing a thing wil it be to this land here ſpoken of, to part with their old earthly forms of Government, and to become ſubject to the kingdom and government of Jeſus Chriſt alone: They look at them as their birthright, and mourn as a man would do for loſſe thereof; and whilſt thus they are mourning over their loſs, they wither and fade, the ſource and ſpring be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing now dried up which formerly kept them freſh and green.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> After which it is ſaid, the whole <hi>World languiſheth fadeth,</hi> that is, the reſt of the Nations fall into a languiſhing conſumption, as the word ſignifieth, and grow ſick of their forms of govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, being ſenſible of their tyranny and oppreſsion, and they alſo fade away like a leaf &amp; wither, and at laſt do fall as leaves in Autumne, which argues the removall of thoſe earthly forms of government, both in that land, and in all the reſt of the Nations and Countries adjacent. And this is the accompliſhment of that word, Heb. 12. 26, 27. <hi>Yet once more I ſhake not the earth only, but alſo heaven. And this, yet once more, ſignifieth the removing of thoſe things that are (or may be) ſhaken, as of things that are made, that thoſe things which cannot be ſhaken may remain.</hi> Thus you ſee the dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtate of earthly governments throughout the world, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially in that land ſpoken of. It now remains to ſhew you, what wil be the condition of that <hi>High One</hi> of the people, of whom it is ſaid, <hi>The moſt High One of the people do languiſh.</hi> The<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> word tranſlated <hi>Moſt High One,</hi> doth properly ſignifie height in the abſtract, but is uſually put for the ſuperlative degree of the concrete, as Pſal. 56. 2. And it ſignifies an exaltation, or lift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:118828:10"/> up in height above the reſt of the people. Concerning which <hi>High one,</hi> it is ſaid <hi>they doe languiſh,</hi> in the plurall number. Which<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> implies, that this <hi>High one</hi> and thoſe that have advanced him to that height, ſhall all of them fall into a conſumption, and lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh. And this holds forth a decay and abatement of ſtrength by degrees, which will come upon them as it is uſual with men in a ling ring diſeaſe.</p>
               <p>Thus you have a brief deſcription of the manifold mutations and changes that will happen to that land inparticular, and to the whole world in general, &amp; laſtly to this <hi>High one</hi> of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and his advancers. In the next verſe follows the ground and cauſe of all theſe evils, to wit, their hypocriſie and apoſtacie.</p>
               <p>Ver. 5. <hi>The land alſo is defiled under the inhabitants thereof.</hi>] The<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> word tranſlated <hi>defiled,</hi> * doth properly ſignify, to diſſemble and play the hypocrite, to ſin fraudulently, ſecretly, malitiouſly; and by a Metaphor, to defile: The meaning thereof is, that the whole land in generall have played the Hypocrites and dealt falſly and fraudulently with God, and defiled themſelves with apoſtacie, as the Prophet proveth afterwards in ſundry particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars. The univerſality of this Hypocriſie and apoſtaſie, ſeemes to extend unto all that inhabit the land: The people, the <hi>High one</hi> of the people, and the Repreſentative of the people; They are all guilty; and this the Prophet proves in three particulars. For firſt, <hi>They have tranſgreſſed the Law,</hi>] to wit, the morall Law. They neither give God his due, nor man his due, which is the ſum of the whole law. They can be zealous when their own in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts are concerned, but where is their zeal againſt open Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies, common ſwearing, groſſe adulteries, notorious whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, horrible oppreſſions, and exactions, and all manner of profanenes? And is not that a ſtrong conviction of their Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie and Apoſtacie? 2ly. <hi>They have changed the Statute.</hi>] The word tranſlated <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>changed,</hi> ſignifiea ſuch a change as doth ſubſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute one thing in the room or ſteed of another. The word <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Buxtorf.</hi>
                  </note> Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute or Ordinance, ſignifies ſuch Statutes and Ordinances as God hath impoſed: And ſometimes it is put for Eccleſiaſticall impoſitions and Statutes, ſuch as concern the affaires of the Church, as the Ceremonies of old did; ſometimes it is put for Civill impoſitions and Statutes, which relate to Civill things; and ſuch were the Judicials. Now ſaith the Prophet, in ſtead of the Statutes and Ordinances which God hath impoſed, they
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118828:10"/> have ſubſtituted Ordinances and impoſitions of their own inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and framing, both in Spirituals and Temporals. This is the changing of the Statute here ſpoken of, and it is a reall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration of their Hypocriſie and Apoſtacie, wherewith he charged them in the firſt words of the verſe. And 3ly. <hi>They have broken the everlaſting covenant.</hi>] This implies an entrance in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſuch a ſolemn Covenant (at leaſt by the Truſtees of the land) which is here called the everlaſting Covenant, and by the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God in every age of the world hath or ought to have been made. Now what is this everlaſting Covenant? doubtleſſe it is to accept Chriſt upon his own termes, to rule over us as our King: according as <hi>Iſaiah</hi> (prophecying alſo of this very age and ſeaſon) ſaith, <hi>Jehovah is our Judge, Jehovah is our Statute maker</hi> (or Legiſlator,) <hi>Jehovah is our King, he will ſave us,</hi> Iſa. 33. 22. This is their ſolemn Covenant, profeſſion, and proteſtation, if God will but bath his ſword in the bloud of their enemies, according as it is ſaid it ſhall be, in the fifth verſe of the next chapter, where he ſpeaks of this very age. Now the Prophet chargeth this land to have broken this Covenant. The word [tranſlated <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>broken,</hi>] ſignifies, to break or make it void, by preſuming it to be a Conditional covenant: The meaning is, they doe evade this Covenant with diſtinctions and qualificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Buxtorf.</hi>
                  </note> and conditions, and ſo break the Covenant which is indeed an everlaſting Covenant and not avoidable by any pretences whatſoever, without guilt of Hypocriſie and Apoſtacie. And therefore when they abſolutely profeſſe and vow and Covenant that they will take Chriſt on his own termes, and that they will have no King but him, no laws but his laws, &amp; afterwards come to diſtinguiſh uppon the meaning, and make the covenant onely a ſtalking-horſe to attaine their own ends; the Prophet tells them plainly, this is Hypocriſie, it is apoſtacie, yea ſuch as defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the whole land. Thus the Prophet deciphers out the ſad changes that ſhall come upon that land, and the cauſes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. The dolefull conſequences follow in the ſeven next enſuing verſes.</p>
               <p>Ver. 6. <hi>Therefore hath the curſe devoured the land, &amp;c.</hi>] Theſe words are an inference upon the former, and ſhew the bitter fruit of their hypocriſie, apoſtaſie, and covenant breaking. The curſe eateth up the land, and as it is ſaid, <hi>Deut. 28. 16, &amp;c.</hi> Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in Citie, curſed in field, curſed in basket and ſtore, &amp;c. but
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:118828:11"/> the curſe here ſpoken of, is a curſe with an oath, becauſe of their<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> perjuries in breach of covenant: for covenants are uſually made with an oath, or curſe, or ſolemn vow in the preſence of God, equivalent to an oath, the Lord himſelf being witneſs of it, and a dreadful avenger of the breach thereof, and <hi>God wil not hold him guiltleſſe that taketh his name in vain, Exod.</hi> 20. 7. Were it but an oath and covenant with men, even ſuch who have advanced us to power, that were broken, God would recompence it, as you may read, <hi>Ezek. 17. 16. As I live (ſaith the Lord Jehovih</hi>) ſpeaking of Chriſt; for ſo the name <hi>Jehovih</hi> is always taken) <hi>Surely in the place of that King that kinged him, whoſe oath he deſpiſed, and whoſe covenant he brake: with him in the midſt of Babylon he ſhall die. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall Pharaoh with his mighty Army and great Company make for him in the war, by raiſing up mounts and building forts to cut off many ſouls: ſeeing he deſpiſed the oath [or curſe] (when lo he had given his hand) and hath done all theſe things, he ſhall not eſcape. Therefore thus ſaith the Lord JEHOVIH, As I live, ſurely mine oath which he hath deſpiſed, and my covenant which he hath broken, even it wil I recompence upon his own head. And I will ſpread my net upon him, and he ſhall be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in my ſnare, and I will bring him to Babylon, and will make him ſuffer puniſhment there for his</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">This pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varication is when a man makes ſemblance to doe one thing, and doth the quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary.</note> 
                  <hi>prevarication wherewith he hath pree<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>varicated againſt me. And all his fugitives, with all his troops, ſhall fall by the ſword, and they that remain ſhall be ſcattered towards all the windes, and ye ſhall know that I Jehovah have ſpoken it.</hi> Men may think it a point of policy to diſſemble in their covenants; and when their ends are attained to break them, but God counts it prophaneneſſe, and therefore this King is called by the Prophet, <hi>Ezek. 21. 25. Thou prophane and wicked Prince of Iſrael.</hi> Let all co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant-breakers read it and tremble, for God hath a net and a ſnare for them which they ſhall not be able to eſcape, were they whole Hoſts and Bands of men. The oath which Chriſt hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken is with a curſe, as if he ſhould ſay, let me not live if I do not recompence ſuch dallying with oaths and covenants upon the heads of all ſuch men. And ſo I ſhall have done with the Oath or Curſe that devoureth the land.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And they that dwell therein are guilty.</hi>] The word tranſlated <hi>Gulty,</hi> properly ſignifies guilt of ſin, as if the prophet ſhould ſay,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> Theſe covenant-breakers (notwithſtanding all the evils that do befall the poore land, will wipe their mouthes like the adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous woman, <hi>Prov.</hi> 30. 20.) and ſay, <hi>I have done, no wicedneſſe.</hi> But
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:118828:11"/> the Prophet holds his hand upon the ſore, tels them, they are guilty of all the wickedneſſe before mentioned, to wit, hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie and diſſimulation both with God and men: apoſtaſie from their firſt principles, breach of their covenants, oaths and proteſtations, whereof God, Angels and Men are witneſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s. And And this is no ſlight matter, for in the end it brings ruine and<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> deſolation, as our tranſlation renders the word. In which ſenſe the word there uſed hath a neer affi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ity with another root which ſignifies to make deſolate. Thus you ſee two ſad conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences of covenant-breaking, to wit, Curſe and Deſolation. Another is the inraging or heating of mens ſpirits, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent of that, to wit, a conſuming and burning up of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants with inteſtine warrs. <hi>Therefore.</hi>] The word <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> here uſed is properly rendred, <hi>Becauſe it is thus,</hi> as if the Prophet ſhould ſay, Becauſe the curſe of God is upon the land for their covenant-breaking, &amp;c. and men ſtill lye under the guilt thereof without repentance and will not be convinced; their ſpirits therefore grow to be overheated and inraged, ſo as the fire of inteſtine warrs doth burn and conſume them. Such is the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catenation of woes and Calamities, upon that poore miſerable land. And yet we are not come to an end of them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Therefore the inhabitants of the Land are inraged.</hi>] The word<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> properly ſignifies to kindle and inflame with internall or exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall heat, ſuch as conſumes the Radicall moiſture. Hence it is ſometimes tranſlated burning or conſuming, which is the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per effect of this heat of ſpirit and wrath. And this will be the ſtate of the Land in generall, onely the <hi>poore little man</hi> will eſcape this rage and fury.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And the poore little man left.</hi>] The word tranſlated <hi>poore man</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> ſignifies a feeble ſorrowful calamitous man: and the word <hi>little,</hi> is a man that is low or little in eſtate, and low in the reputation of the world. God chooſeth the fooliſh things of this world, to confound the wiſe; and God hath choſen the weak things of this world to confound the things which are mighty; and baſe things of the world, and things which are deſpiſed, hath God choſen; and things that are not, to bring to nought things that are, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 27, 28. The meaning I conceive may be this, either that the afflictions of theſe times will be ſuch, as all univerſally through the Nation will be reduced unto ſorrow and calamity: So that the people who were formerly renowned and dreaded of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:118828:12"/> all Nations, will now become mean and deſpicable. Or elſe the meaning may be this, that in the midſt of theſe combuſtions and tumults, God will reſerve a company of poor ſorrowfull mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, which for eſtates are weak and feeble, and for repute in the world are mean and deſpicable; even theſe ſhall be reſerved, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as it is writ, <hi>Zeph. 3. 12. I will alſo leave in the midſt of thee, an afflicted and poore people; and they ſhall truſt in the Name of Jehovah.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe deſpicable ones which the world thinks to be deluded with an apprehenſion of a fifth Monarchy, or Kingdome of Chriſt, theſe poore men are left: they eſcape the rage wherewith the men of the world are incenſed, and carry it in all humility, meekneſſe, patience, and ſimplicity, (without any ſecret plots &amp; deſignes) and are of a ſweet, peaceable, quiet, calm and cool tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, when all the land is in a hot burning feaver. If they looſe their eſtates, they bear it patiently: if their lives and liberties, they are (like their Maſter Chriſt) dumb before the ſhea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, not opening their mouthes: yea, ſo farre are they from being inraged and incenſed with the ſad calamities that happen, that on the contrary they lift up their heads and rejoyce, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that their redemption draweth nigh. Call them what you will, Presbyterians, Puritans, Independents, Anabaptiſts, Fifth Monarchy-men, giddy headed fellows, or what the world plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> they are not moved, their ſpirts will not be chafed or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verheated, but they patiently bear it all with an amiable, quiet and calm ſpirit, and are not aſhamed of the Croſſe of Chriſt; they rather rejoyce that they are counted worthy to ſuffer reproaches and impriſonments for their Lord and Maſter, and for their hope &amp; faith, in the word of his truth: They know that after they have ſuffered with him, and for him, they ſhall aſſuredly reigne with him: and therefore they ſtill wait for and pray for, and preach for, and ſuffer for the Kingdome of Chriſt, which they know will aſſuredly come, and is now at hand, even at the doores.</p>
               <p>Thus have you a brief, yet full deſcription of the State of that poor miſerable Land, whereof the Prophet ſpeaketh; and the various mutations of Government in that Land, together with the ſeverall ſteps and degrees of all thoſe Changes, and the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes thereof, and the Curſe that comes upon the Land, and the fruits thereof, and upon the inhabitants of the ſame; onely a ſmal lemnant excepted. And now followes the Judgement of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:118828:12"/> God upon their choiſeſt Comforts, their forreign Trade and Shipping, verſe 7, 8, 9. and upon the great Citie or Metropolis of the Land, verſe 10, 11, 12.</p>
               <p>Verſe 7. <hi>The new wine mourneth, the Vine languiſheth, &amp;c.</hi>] This verſe and the two following verſes, doe hold forth Gods blaſting hand upon all their chiefeſt comforts under theſe Metaphoricall expreſsions. And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the Prophet ſaith, <hi>The new wine mourneth, &amp;c.</hi> It ſeems to imply a decay or obſtruction of their forreign Trade, and alſo of their ſhipping by which ſuch comforts are imported, their mirth and muſicke alſo, with all their jollity, will be blaſted, by reaſon of the heavie judgements of God<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> upon them.</p>
               <p>Verſe 10. 11, 12. <hi>The City</hi> Tohu <hi>is broken</hi>] The word tranſlated <hi>Tohu</hi> doth properly ſignifie an Exiſtence of Being without form or order, as I have obſerved upon Gen. 1. 1. where that word is firſt uſed. and is in our En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Bibles tranſlated, <hi>Without form.</hi> This argues the Factions, diſtractions, and Diviſions of the Citizens of this great Citie within themſelves; ſome will be for one party, ſome for another party, and others for neither. Inſomuch as no man dare keep his doores open, nor ſuffer any to come in. This faction and diviſion within, expoſeth both the City and ſuburbs to breaking, plundering, aſtoniſhment and deſolation. And all this in a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall manner ſpoken of the Metropolis, or chiefe Citie of the Land, according to the uſuall manner of Scripture.</p>
               <p>And thus you have an ample deſcription of the calamities which will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall both City and Countrey, Government and Governor of theſe Iſlands. Which Cataſtrophe being ended, the Prophet in the next verſe puts in a word of comfort and ſupport unto the poore deſpiſed ones of Chriſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned.</p>
               <p>Ver. 13. <hi>When thus it ſhall be, in the midſt of the Land among the people, and as it were the ſhaking of an Olive tree, as the Gleaning of Grapes when the Vintage is done.</hi>] Theſe words hold forth two things. 1. That this time of Gods Judgement is his vintage; And if you compare it with <hi>Rev.</hi> 14. 19, 20. it will appeare to be a bloudy vintage, a vintage of red wine indeed. And ſo I conceive the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets meaning by this Metaphor, to be this. That ſince the people of the Land here ſpoken of, would not accept the opportunity which God ſet before them, of moulding themſelves a new, according to the revealed will of Chriſt in his word; but would ſtill reteine their old ancient cuſtomes and formes of admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of their own modelling; the Lord is put upon a neceſſity (as we may ſpeak with reverence) to ſcruice them and preſſe them as Olives are preſſed, and to tread them as grapes are troden in the wine-preſſe, ere they will come off to a profeſſed ſubjection to Jeſus Chriſt: Yet after they have been throughly harrazed and broken under ſeveral forms of Government one after another of their own forming and modelling, God will produce pretious Oyle and Wine at length, and then they will be willing to liſten to thoſe poore contemptible perſons, which they before ſlighted, as fifth Monarchy men, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And now they will be glad to ſubmit to the quiet, peaceable and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Government of Chriſt, having taſted and found by wofull expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, the inſtability, imperfection and unrighteouſneſſe of all other forms and adminiſtrations.</p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:118828:13"/>
               <p>Secondly, theſe words hold forth unto us the diſtinguiſhing love of God to a poore remnant of deſpiſed ones, which the world hates. For whilſt God is thus preſſing the fat ones and great ones of the land (which number up Riches as the duſt of the earth, and reare up Trophies of honor &amp; greatneſſe to eternize their memories) I ſay, whilſt God caſteth theſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Wine<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> preſſe of his wrath, he reſerves to himſelfe a handfull of theſe poore mournfull men, who wait for the kingdom of Chriſt, and pray for it, and preach for it; and theſe he ſaveth from the preſſe, and reſerveth for afterwards, that they may glorifie him with their light, when the indignation is overpaſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and when the vintage is done.</p>
               <p>Verſe 14. Then ſhall <hi>Theſe lift up their voyce and ſing with a Divine Majeſty</hi> the ſong of <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Lamb, Rev. 15. 3 and from all quarters of the land, yea from the Navie and Maritime coaſts and haven Towns, ſhall their voyce be heard.</p>
               <p>Verſe 15. <hi>Wherefore glorifie ye Jehovah with</hi> URIM, &amp;c. The word tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated <hi>Wherefore,</hi> doth properly ſignifie, <hi>Becauſe it is thus;</hi> ſpeaking to the little Remnant afore mentioned, as who ſhould ſay, ſince God hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed ſuch diſtinguiſhing love towards you, to preſerve you in the midſt of the flames, and reſerved you to ſing forth his praiſes when the vintage is done, therefore glorifie ye Jehovah with URIM, all ye that dwell in thoſe Iſlands. The word URIM is tranſlated in our Engliſh Bibles <hi>Tyres,</hi> but not ſo fitly. Never doe the tranſlators ever render that word in that ſence, ſave onely in this place. Indeed the word [UR] in the ſingular number i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſed for fire; but never is URIM in the plurall number ſo taken: Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it is a truth that the Saints ſhould glorifie the Lord in the fires, and in the waters alſo.</p>
               <p>URIM and THUMMIM were two pretious ſtones (as is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived) which were purpoſely made by God, and appointed to be ſet in the Breaſt-plate of Judgement, <hi>Exod.</hi> 28. 30. to manifeſt the counſel of God unto his people, when they enquired of him in dark and doubtfull caſes, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther God did give anſwer by that URIM, ſhewing them, as in a glaſſe, a verball anſwer to that which was inquired, or how elſe, it is not manfeſt. For my own part, I rather conceive that thoſe URIM and THUMMIM (whatſoever they were) being worn by the High Prieſt in his Breaſt-plate, as an ordinance and inſtitution of Chriſt under that Pedagogie of <hi>Moſes,</hi> were as Symbols to aſſure the people that their <hi>High Prieſt</hi> ſhould be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned with divine light from Chriſt Jeſus, to give a clear and perfect reſolution to the matter inquired. And in confidence hereof, the people did <hi>Aquieſce</hi> in the anſwer of the <hi>High Prieſt,</hi> ſo that by URIM in this place, I do underſtand nothing elſe but divine and heavenly light from Chriſt. And this is that which the Prophet calls upon them here to glorifie God withall. But yet obſerve the punctation of the word, which is with a ſhort vowel not with a long vowel; to ſhew us that the light which ſhines forth in thoſe Iſlands, will not be ſo full and cleare as afterwards, when the Jewes are called; but yet it will be a heavenly and Divine light. And the Prophet would have the Saints in thoſe Iſlands, to glorifie God with that <hi>light</hi> they have received, and improve it to the benefit of the whole Land, which by this Time will be prepared to receive it. Which argues, that the Land whereof the Prophet ſpeaketh will abound with much divine and heavenly light. And now it will be a fit ſeaſon to hold it forth.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:118828:13"/> Tell them now of the Kingdom of Chriſt, and the righteouſneſs and perfection of his Laws and adminiſtrations both in Churches and Civil State, and they will now liſten to it. And now let every one come and hold forth the light he hath receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from above, and add light unto light: For as it is in a roome where many lights are added together, they yield a great light; ſo it is in this caſe: only ſee that the light you hold forth be Divine and Heavenly light, grounded on the word of God; and let your words be as the Oracles of God. Come not with falſe lights or falſe fire; bring no kitchin-fire of your own invention, but let all your light have the ſtamp of God up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, and it will tend much to the honor of Chriſt. And thus you ſhould glorifie God with light.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Even the name of Jehovah the God of Iſrael.</hi>] Theſe words do hint unto us the Church-order and Government, wherein theſe precious ſouls are united; and therefore he exhorts them to glorifie God, as the God of Iſrael: That is, a God in cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with his Church. And indeed this will be the great and principal work of that age, and of thoſe Chriſtians before ſpoken of; they will improve their light, for the gathering of the people of that <hi>land</hi> into due order, and into holy Covenant with God and one with another. For that is the right way of advancing the Kingdom of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Verſ. 16. <hi>From the wing of the land,</hi> &amp;c.] The wing is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times put for the utmoſt part of the land. And ſo the meaning will be this: The Saints in the utmoſt confines and borders of the land ſhall ſing ſongs. Or elſe, by <hi>the wing of the land</hi> may be underſtood the Churches in <hi>New England</hi> beyond the Seas (whither they have ſailed as with wings) even they ſhall ſing, and keep dayes of thanſgiving, when they ſhall hear what God hath done in the land here ſpoken of, and the report of it ſhall be carryed back from thence. They will applaud the wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful works of God in that land, and acknowledge the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Gods diſpenſations in behalf of his own people. And thus you ſee the joyful and comfortable iſſue of all theſe ſad ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities foregoing.</p>
               <p>But the prophet then looking back upon the perfidious treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of thoſe who had been chiefly inſtrumental in all the changes
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:118828:14"/> and calamities aforementioned, he breaks forth into a moſt bitter lamentation for the ſame, crying out, <hi>My leanneſs my lean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, wo unto me, the treacherous dealers have dealt treach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erouſly, yea the treacherous dealers have dealt very treach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erouſly.</hi> The prophet was ſo deeply affected herewith, that he pined away with grief, crying, <hi>My leanneſs, my leanneſs.</hi> And the reaſon of this his bitter complaint is, becauſe thoſe that were betruſted by God, and by the people of the land, to have reſcued them out of the hands of the Tyranny of the firſt Government, and to have ſet up the Government of Chriſt, when the firſt Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment and alſo the ſecond were diſſolved, have betrayed their truſt, and dealt perfidiouſly from firſt to laſt, carrying on a ſecret deſign of their own; and have improved their power and truſt, to enſnare the land.</p>
               <p>Verſe 17. <hi>FEARE, and the PIT, and the SNARE are upon thee,</hi> &amp;c] Theſe words. I take to be Metaphorical expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, to hold forth unto us the various forms of Government in that land, and the nature of them: For I finde theſe phraſes uſed in the like ſenſe, <hi>Jer.</hi> 48. 43 44. where the prophet ſpeaks of the various mutations of Government, that ſhould come up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Moab.</hi> And <hi>Lam.</hi> 3. 47. where he alſo ſpeaks of the changes that befel the Kingdom of Iſrael, after the death of <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiah;</hi> and ſo I take it in this place. And you ſhall obſerve how the prophet Marſhals them in order. The firſt form of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment he calls <hi>FEAR</hi>] which implies the terror and Tyranny of<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> the firſt Government; putting the effect for the cauſe by a Meto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nymie. The ſecond he calls a <hi>PIT.</hi>] The word here uſed,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> ſignifies properly ſuch a pit, as is digged under ground: which implies that this ſecond form of Government, was purpoſely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived, to obviate the Tyranny of the firſt. And it is called a <hi>PIT,</hi> to ſhew that it is of a lower conſtitution then the former was. Yea, ſuch a <hi>pit</hi> it is, as may yield ſome ſhelter or hiding-place from the purſuit of a Tyrant, as may appear, from the uſe of the ſame word, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17. 9. where <hi>Huſhai</hi> ſpeaking of <hi>David,</hi> when he was purſued by that Tyrant <hi>Abſalom,</hi> he ſaith, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, he is hid in ſome pit.</hi> And the third form of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, he calls a <hi>SNARE</hi>] The word properly ſignifies ſuch a<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> ſnare as fowlers uſe to lay to catch the birds withal, either by the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:118828:14"/> foot or by the neck, from which they cannot deliver themſelves. Which ſnare the fowlers uſe to cover with chaff or ſome ſuch thing, ſo as the birds ſhall not ſee the ſnare, till they be taken in it. Which doth imply, that this third form of Government in that land, for the nature of it, ſhall be a <hi>ſnare.</hi> And for the manner of errecting the ſame, it ſhall be ſecret and hidden; co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered over with ſuch ſpecious and fair pretences, that men ſhall not diſcerne their <hi>Snare,</hi> till they be taken in it. And being once taken, it will be difficult to reſcue and deliver themſelves, ſuch will be the ſtrength of it. <hi>FEAR, and the Pit, and the SNARE, are upon thee, O inhabitants of the land</hi>] He doth not ſay, Oh inhabitant, but <hi>Oh inhabitants</hi> in the plural number, to ſhew that univerſally all of them, and particularly every of them, ſhall be taken in this <hi>Snare.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Verſ. 18. <hi>And he that aſcends out of the midſt of the PIT, ſhall be taken in the SNARE</hi>] This aſcending argues that the form of Government is of a higher conſtitution, in regard of the external pomp and glory of the fame, then the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment foregoing was. And ſuch will be the ſubtile and curious contrivement of the ſame, as they will catch all men in ſnares that reſiſt them, and ſuch as cannot comply with their new-deviſed power. So the Prophet hath done with the threefold form of Government in that land, and the treachery of the inſtruments. And in the words enſuing tells you that God looks on all this while: &amp; though men drive on their deſignes in all that foregoeth, yet God will at length turn about their actings, to accompliſh his grand deſign. For ſaith the prophet, The windows of that <hi>MOST HIGH</hi> are opened.] The <hi>moſt high</hi> here mentioned, is the Lord himſelfe, who only is the <hi>MOST HIGH</hi> Pſal. 56. 2. It is Gods attribute, and therefore let mortal men tremble to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume Gods title to themſelves, except<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> God give it them. <hi>The windows from this MOST HIGH are opened</hi>] As who ſhould ſay, God looks out of his latteſſes (ſpeaking after the manner of men) and he ſees the treachery of the inſtruments in all theſe mutations; and therefore he reſolves to overturn all thoſe earthly mouldy forms of their own deviſing, and by cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ſteps and degrees, to make way for an utter abolition of them all. Now the ſteps and degrees God taketh for removal
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:118828:15"/> of thoſe three ſorts of Government in that land, are in number ſeven, to wit, <hi>ſhaking, bruiſing, breaking<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> diſplacing, reel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, removing, falling.</hi> And all of them do aptly expreſs the ſeveral ſteps and gradations which God taketh towards the removal, and utter abolition of the old heavens and old earth in <hi>that land.</hi> The firſt, I take to relate unto the firſt and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Government of that land. The three next ſteps, unto the ſecond. And the three laſt, have relation unto the laſt form of Government.</p>
               <p>We may not ſuppoſe that the Prophet affected to ſhew his elocution in Rhetorical ſtrains of ſpeech. For that would not become the holineſs of the Prophet, nor the matter in hand. Neither is it likely that he heaps up words by way of <hi>Exegeſis</hi> and amplification onely. For then he could have choſen ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry more words<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or other words that would have been very comprehenſive alſo. But I take it that the Holy Spirit that guided him, did not call out ſuch choice expreſſions as would moſt aptly hold forth the ſeveral ſteps which he intended to make, in removal of their earthly forms of Government; and yet with ſuch a Divine elegancy, as no art of Rhetorick can exceed it, if you conſider the words in their proper lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage. I ſhall therefore give a brief touch of them all in their order.</p>
               <p>And firſt of the firſt word. <hi>The foundations of the earth</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>do ſhake</hi> or <hi>are ſhaken.</hi>] This I conceive doth relate unto the firſt and ancient form of Government, which the Prophet calls FEARE: and here he makes his pauſe, or full point, to intimate, that this ſhaking of the foundations, put a period to that Government. And ſo the Apoſtle interprets the word <hi>ſhaking,</hi> Heb. 12. Where he ſaith, <hi>It ſignifies the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moval of thoſe things that may be ſhaken.</hi> So then the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king here ſpoken of, ſignifies a removal of that firſt Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as hath been ſaid. And the ſhaking of the foundations doth import no leſs.</p>
               <p>Verſ. 19 <hi>The land is ſore bruiſed, the land is utterly broken, the land is quite diſplaced.</hi>] Theſe words I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand do hold forth to us a threefold gradation, leading to a
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:118828:15"/> diſſolution of the ſecond Government called the PIT. The firſt ſtep is expreſſed in theſe words, <hi>The land is ſore bruiſed;</hi> ſpeaking of the repreſentative of the land. The word Tranſlated <hi>ſore bruiſed,</hi> in the Hebrew is, <hi>The land in bruiſing is bruiſed.</hi> Which word properly ſignifies bruiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> by colliſion of two hard things together, <hi>Jer.</hi> 10. 9. And it alſo implies that this bruiſing ſhall be by the exerciſe of the power of the ſword, as may appear from the <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2. 9. where the ſame word is uſed. And that rod of <hi>iron,</hi> meanes the power of the ſword, <hi>Revl.</hi> 19. 17. So that the meaning as I conceive is this, that by the power of the <hi>Militia,</hi> the Repreſentative of that land ſhall be ſore brui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. The next ſtep is, <hi>They ſhall be utterly broken</hi>] or, in breaking they ſhall be broken. The word properly ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> to evacuate or break a thing upon ſome ſemblance or pretence of condition; which argues that there will be ſome condition ground, or reaſon, pretended for the breach and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of the Repreſentative of that land. The third ſtep is this, <hi>The Land is quite diſplaced</hi>] or moved out of<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> place: An argument that after the diſſolution of the firſt Repreſentative, there will be a ſecond. But that is here ſaid to be <hi>moved quite out of place:</hi> Or, as it is in the Hebrew, <hi>In moving out of place, it ſhall be moved out of place.</hi> The word here uſed doth properly ſignifie to move a thing out of its place. And the phraſe ſeems to imply ſuch a motion as from the firſt calling of them together to their diſſolution, is quite out of courſe, and not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeing with the ancient cuſtomes of the Repreſentatives of that land. And thus you are come to the end of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Repreſentative, and the ſecond form of Government together. The third kind of Government<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which is called a SNARE, followeth. And you have three ſteps and degrees to the ablition of that.</p>
               <p>Verſe 20. <hi>The land ſhall reel to and fro like a drunkard.</hi>]<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> Theſe words ſhew the giddy, tottering, unſetled condition of the land under the third kind of Government. The word
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:118828:16"/> ſignifies the nodding or trembling of the head. And it argues the unſtayed giddineſs of the repreſentative, reeling (as a man in drink) ſometimes this way, ſometime that way.</p>
               <p>The next ſtep is, <hi>They ſhall be removed as a cottage</hi>] The word Tranſlated <hi>removed,</hi> properly ſignifies to wander as a Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grant<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> or Vagabond. It was the curſe of <hi>Cain,</hi> Gen. 4. 12<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 14, 16. <hi>A vagabond ſhalt thou be upon earth.</hi> And now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the woful ſtate of the land here ſpoken of; they ſhall wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der here, and wander there, and know not where to reſt. The phraſe I conceive, doth expreſs the conſternation and dejection of their ſpirits, under the heavy preſſure of their ſins (as it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows in the next words) and Gods juſt indignation againſt them for the ſame. And now they are (like <hi>Cain</hi>) afraid of all kinds of Government having felt already, the ſad and woful effects and fruits of one after another, and finding nothing but <hi>FEAR,</hi> and the <hi>PIT,</hi> and the <hi>SNARE</hi> in them all: God hath ſo blaſted all earthly Governments and the glory of them, that now the poor land is afraid to make proof of them any more. They are gotten into the land of <hi>NOD,</hi> a vagrant condition, by reaſon of their tranſgreſſion, as it is in the next words, <hi>For the tranſgreſſion thereof ſhall be heavy upon it</hi>] Theſe words give us the reaſon of all theſe woes and calamities, to wit, their tranſgreſſion, and their impenitency under the ſame, becauſe they would not hearken to the meſſengers of Chriſt. The word tranſlated <hi>tranſgreſſion,</hi> doth<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> properly ſignifie ſuch a tranſgreſſion as is againſt light, and ſuch as is accompanyed with obſtinacy and contumacy. It is a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound of <hi>Pride and Rebellion;</hi> Or as <hi>Aben Ezra</hi> ſaith, it is an exemption of a mans ſelf from a lawful power, and an oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt the ſame. The meaning I take to be this; that the land here ſpoken of, counts it ſelf free, and exempted from the juriſdiction of Chriſts Laws and Statutes, and aſſumes to it ſelf a legiſlative power, which is here called <hi>tranſgreſſion,</hi> or contu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy againſt the light held forth by the ſervants of Chriſt. And this lies heavy upon the land, as an inſupportable load or burden that preſſeth it down. For (I conceive) that here will be fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led (in ſome degree at leaſt) the word of the Lord, <hi>Rev. 14. 19. And the Angel thruſt in his ſicle into the earth, and gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the vine of the earth, and caſt it into the winepreſs of the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:118828:16"/> wrath of God. And the winepreſs was troden without the City, and blood came out of the winepreſs, even unto the horſe-bridles<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> by the ſpace of a thouſand and ſix hundred fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs.</hi> May not this City well be called the City of confuſion, as our Engliſh Tranſlation reads it? And now follows the third and laſt ſtep under the third kind of Government: <hi>It ſhall fall, and never riſe any more</hi>] Theſe words put a period to the third and laſt kinde of Government in that land. <hi>The heavens paſs away with a noiſe the elements ſhall melt with fervent heat, the earth alſo, and the works that are therein, ſhall be burnt up<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> 2 Pet. 3. 10. And now will be fulfilled that word of <hi>Iſaiah,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 65. 17.</note> who ſaith, the old heaven and earth ſhall not come upon their heart. They will henceforth have no more to do with earthly forms of Government, but now they are prepared to ſubmit un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſts Government and adminiſtration, according to his word alone. And when thus they are aſhamed and confound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for their folly, in all their civil adminiſtrations, and Church-adminiſtrations alſo; then they ſet up Chriſts plain, pure, and perfect adminiſtrations in both. And this was Chriſts maine ſcope and deſign, from the very firſt mutation and change in the beginning of the Chapter; which being now attained unto in ſome good meaſure in that land, behold, Chriſt takes a ſpeedy courſe with that HIGH ONE and his hoſt, which have been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumental in all theſe ſad changes, and have obſtructed the work of Chriſt in that Nation.</p>
               <p>Verſe 21. <hi>And it ſhall come to paſs in that day</hi>] To wit, when God hath ſubdued the ſpirits of the people, and prepared them (as waxe) to receive the impreſſion of a new form of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and now they are willing the Government ſhould lie<note place="margin">Iſa. 9. 6. Iſa. 33. 22.</note> upon the ſhoulder of Chriſt; and are reſolved, <hi>Jehovah</hi> ſhall be their Legiſlator, and not a Repreſentive of their own. Now I ſay, when it is thus, <hi>Jehovah will puniſh the hoaſt of that MOST HIGH ONE, with that MOST HIGH ONE</hi>] To wit, him that in the fourth verſe is called the MOST HIGH ONE of the people. And it ſeems, that this <hi>Moſt high one</hi> hath the command of the Militia of that land; wherefore the Militia is called his Militia or hoſt. It may alſo be called his Militia, becauſe they have been inſtrumental to advance him to
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:118828:17"/> that <hi>height</hi> or <hi>highneſs,</hi> and ſo the fourth verſe ſeems to intimate. Or if you will, it may include both. But take it which way you pleaſe, the Lord <hi>Jehovah</hi> that gives all <hi>Beings</hi> their exiſtence, and gives a <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> to all his judgements, will viſit the <hi>Militia</hi> of that MOST HIGH ONE, with the MOST HIGH ONE. You may either underſtand it thus, that God will make that MOST HIGH ONE an inſtrumental cauſe of the Hoſts puniſhment; or, that he will puniſh the Hoſt in that MOST HIGH ONE, as being the head and chief of them: or elſe, that he will puniſh them both together. The phraſe is very obſervable, and though our Engliſh tranſlation read it otherwiſe, <hi>That God will puniſh the hoſt of the high ones that are on high,</hi> yet it is not ſo proper. For 1. The<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> word is there uſed in the ſingular number, not in the plural. 2. There is affixed an Emphaſis to the word, the Hoſt of that <hi>moſt high one.</hi> And 3. The word there uſed, ſignifies properly <hi>height</hi> in the abſtract; And is as much as if you ſhould ſay in our Engliſh Idiome, that MOST HIGH ONE. And in propriety of ſpeech, there can be but <hi>one Moſt High:</hi> Wherefore God aſſumes it as his own proper title, verſ. 18. And <hi>David</hi> attributes it to God, <hi>Pſal. 56. 2. Oh thou MOST HIGH.</hi> Let mortal ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful men therefore tremble to arrogate ſuch titles of God unto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, unleſs God give it them. The place of the puniſhment of this MOST HIGH ONE, and his hoſt, together with the Kings of the earth, it is in this world. God will not reſpite it unto the world to come. For ſo much is implyed in that phraſe, <hi>upon the earth.</hi> And well it is for them, if they may receive their puniſhment in this world onely. What the kind of their puniſhment ſhall be, is not expreſſed, ſave onely that <hi>they ſhall be gathered with a gathering, a priſoner for the dungeon, and ſhall be ſhut up in priſon.</hi> Or, as we uſe to ſay, ſhall be cloſe priſoners. And whether that onely ſhall be their puniſhment, or whether they ſhall be reſerved unto further puniſhment afterwards, is not very clear from the text. Poſſibly, if they then repent, as <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> did, God may ſhew them mercy.</p>
               <p>Verſ. 23. <hi>Then the Moon ſhall be confounded, and the Sun aſhamed.</hi>] The word tranſlated <hi>confounded,</hi> doth ſignifie to digg through the earth, as men uſe to do, untill they come to a <hi>living ſpring.</hi> And ſo the word is uſed, <hi>Gen. 26. 18. And</hi> Iſaac <hi>digged again the wells of water, which they had digged in the dayes of</hi> Abraham <hi>his father.</hi> The meaning is, God will ſo digg through all thoſe earthly, mouldy, carnal politicks of civil Government in that land, till he ſhew them at length, the limpid clear fountain, and living ſpring of righteouſneſs and Judgement out of the word of Chriſt, ſo that they will be confounded with ſhame at all their former mouldy principles, after which they have walked in all their former adminiſtrations.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And the Sunne ſhall be aſhamed</hi>] The Churches of Chriſt, even the moſt reformed, ſhall then bluſh, to ſee how far they fall ſhort of the Primitive inſtitution. Thus will God ſhame them, when he begins to ſet up the Government of his Son in this, and in other of the Nations. And ſo I come to the time
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:118828:17"/> when all theſe things ſhall be fulfilled; when God will put a period unto all earthly forms of Government in the land here ſpoken of, and in the reſt of the Nations, and when God will viſit that MOST HIGH ONE, and his Hoſt, and the Kings of the neighbouring Nations. It is [<hi>when Jehovah of Hoſts ſhall Reign:</hi>] you may underſtand the word tranſlated <hi>when,</hi> or <hi>for,</hi> either as an Adverb of time, and ſo it ſhews forth the ſeaſon wherein theſe things ſhal come to paſs: Or you may take it for a Conjunction cauſal, and ſo it ſhew forth both the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal efficient cauſe of all that hath been ſpoken before, and alſo the main ſcope and end, or the main deſign which God had in hand, and aimed at in all theſe mutations in Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and Civil State; to wit, <hi>That</hi> Jehovah might Reign, and ſo that word is alſo uſed. And whereas it is ſaid, <hi>when</hi> Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vah ſhal Reign; or <hi>for</hi> Jehovah Reigneth: or <hi>that</hi> Jehovah may Reign; and there makes a diſtinction, it argues there will be ſome beginning of Chriſts Reign in that Land, and in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Nations of the Gentiles, before the calling of the Jews, but the moſt glorious manifeſtation of Chriſts Kingly power both in Church and State, will be reſerved for his ancient people the Jews, when they are called home again.</p>
               <p>In brief therefore to gather up the ſence of the words; it is as if the Prophet ſhould have ſaid, after Chriſt hath proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by all the forementioned gradations to diſſipate the old Heaven, and old Earth; to wit, their civil, and Church admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrations of their own invention, and to ſet up new Heavens, and new Earth, new adminiſtrations in them both, according to his Word: Then <hi>Jehovah</hi> the Lord of Hoſts, the Lord Jeſus Chriſt wil Reign in that Nation whereof the Prophet ſpeaks, and then he wil puniſh the Hoſt of that <hi>MOST HIGH ONE,</hi> and that <hi>HIGH ONE</hi> both together, and ſo proceed to the reſt of the Nations, and will there rule and Reign as King in Mount Zyon, and in Jeruſalem, in Church, and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth throughout the Nations. But moſt gloriouſly before his Antients the ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> to whom God hath of old promiſed, and ſworn, that his Seed ſhould poſſeſs the gate of his enemies <hi>Gen:</hi> 22. 17. And indeed God ſhewed to <hi>Abraham</hi> as
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:118828:18"/> in a Type or ſhadow, what he would do in the ends of the world, in ſubduing all the four Monarchies, and giving the Kingdom and greatneſs thereof to <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeed. For in the 14 of <hi>Geneſis</hi> you read of four Kings, to wit, <hi>Amraphel</hi> King of <hi>Shinar, Ariech</hi> King of <hi>Elleaſer, Chederlaomer</hi> King of <hi>Elam,</hi> and <hi>Tiddal</hi> King of Nations, whom <hi>Abraham</hi> purſued to reſcue his Kinſman <hi>Lot,</hi> and overcame them and ſlew them. Theſe four Kings were the root (as I may ſay) of the four Monarchies, which in after-times became afflictive to the Church of God. And the fal of theſe was prefigured in the overthrow of thoſe which <hi>Melchiſedeck</hi> doth ſo congratulate with a bleſſing from the <hi>most High God</hi> poſſeſſor of Heaven and Earth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In Mount Zyon, and in Jeruſalem,</hi>] I wil not deny that Mount Zyon and Jeruſalem are here literally meant; for it is an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deniable truth that Chriſt wil Reign there. But withal I take it that by Mount Zion, and Jeruſalem is here intended the Church and civil State, not in Jury only, but in all other the Nations. For <hi>Mount Zyon</hi> is often put for the Church, as <hi>Pſal:</hi> 87. 2. 5, 6, Jehovah <hi>loves the gates of Zyon, more then all the dwellings of</hi> Jacob. <hi>And of Zyon it ſhall be ſaid, this and that man was born in her.</hi> Jehovah <hi>wil count when he writeth the people: this man was born there.</hi> And Pſal. 128. 5. Jehovah <hi>ſhal bleſs thee out of Z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on,</hi> that is, out of his Church. And Jeruſalem is put for civil State where Judgment is adminiſtred, Pſal: 122. 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7. <hi>There are the Thrones of judgment, the Thrones of the houſe of</hi> David, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Pallaces and Thrones of Judgment are not for the Church, but for the civil State. And thus you have a ſweet cloſe after all the ſad calamities and changes of that Nation, which God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>lled out as a ſtage to act this tragical Comedy upon; cloſing up al in a glorious adminiſtration of Chriſts aimable, peaceable, and righteous reign over all the world, but moſt gloriouſly before his antient people the Jews.</p>
               <p>Having thus briefly unfolded the chapter in a way of Ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>plication, I ſhall in a few words cloſe up all in a word or two of Application, analogically, and leave it to the Reader to inlarge upon the ſame in his own private meditations.</p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:118828:18"/>
               <p>Firſt, therefore let it be for admonition to all the Nations of the world if my voice would reach them. Beware of reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting<note place="margin">
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe 1.</note> the Kingdom of Chriſt Jeſus, leſt he tear you in pieces, and there be none to deliver. Beware of abuſing, and mocking and impriſoning his ſervants, and Meſſengers, leſt the wrath of God ariſe, and there be no remedy, 2 <hi>Chro:</hi> 36. 26. Beware of breach of Oath, proteſtations, and Covenants, for God will not hold him guiltleſs that taketh his Name in vain, <hi>Exod:</hi> 20. 7. were it but breach of Covenant with men, even with ſuch as have advanced you, and put you in truſt, and impow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red you, God wil not bear it, Chriſt hath taken an Oath upon it with a curſe. Let me not live if I be nor avenged upon ſuch deſpiſers of Oaths, and Covenants. And he wil ſpread his NET upon them, and take them in his SNARE, <hi>Ezek:</hi> 17. 20.</p>
               <p>2ly. Repent of all you Apoſtacies, and Hipocriſie, and of your breach of the <hi>Everlaſting Covenant.</hi> For behold King Jeſus with a Crown of gold on his head is gone forth already with a fickle in his hand, and hath begun to reap, <hi>Rev:</hi> 14 14, 15. But yet there is another Angel ſhortly to go forth of the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple which is in Heaven, and if the word of command be once given, he wil reap you with a Witneſs, and caſt you into the Wine preſs of the wrath of God, til the blood come out to the Horſe bridles, <hi>Rev:</hi> 14. 17, 18, 19, 20. therefore let the City and country repent, let high and low repent as <hi>Niniveh</hi> did in ſack cloath and aſhes if ſo be you may find mercy in that hour.</p>
               <p>3ly. Affect not to change one earthly form of Government for another, but let the enſample of the Land wherof the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſpeaks, be a warning to you, you will find either FEAR or a PIT, or a SNARE in all Governments, that are not of Chriſts moulding, or elſe you wil find a Wine preſs of Gods wrath in the cloſe: Therefore when you reſolve to change, (as undoubtedly you will) be perſwaded to change your earthly and imperfect Governments, for that heavenly, perfect, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting Government of Chriſt which hitherto hath been a matter of ſcorn to the world, and the Lord perſwade <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet</hi> to dwel in the Tents of <hi>Shem.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:118828:19"/>
               <p>Secondly, let me ſpeak a word or two to the mourners in<note place="margin">
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n,</hi> even to the poor deſpiſed Flock of Chriſt that wait for, and preach for, and pray for the coming of his Kingdom. 1. Take ye the courſe which this Prophet directs, Iſa: 20. 17. <hi>Come ye my people, enter thou into thy chambers, and ſhut thy doors about thee: hide thy ſelf as it were for a little moment, until the indignation be overpast.</hi> The words are weighty, and ſuited for theſe times, [<hi>Enter thou.</hi>] that is let every one of the people of God enter. It is a word of command from God, and requires obedience in us. <hi>Enter into thy chambers.</hi> Gods people have ſeveral cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers to retire into for ſafety in this caſe. 1. They have a cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of <hi>Meditation</hi> into which they do retire themſelves in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Soliloquies with God, <hi>Gen: 24. 63. Iſaac</hi> went into the field to meditate upon the word of God, and his gratious promiſes to his Father and to himſelf, and Gods various diſpenſations about him. And he ſhut the dores againſt all worldly cogita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and imployments for that ſeaſon. <hi>David</hi> was frequent in this duty, eſpecially in the perſecuting times of <hi>Saul</hi> I may cal this the chamber of Gods preſence, where God reveals much of his cabinet counſels to his ſervants, as men uſe to do to their friends in their private chambers. 2ly. There is a chamber of <hi>prayer, Matt: 6. 6. When thou prayeſt enter into thy cloſet and ſhut the doors, and pray to thy Father which is in ſecret.</hi> Here you unboſome your ſelves, and poure out your ſouls before him fully and freely. And truly Chriſtians never more need then now. And this a chamber of <hi>ſafety,</hi> you know how <hi>Moſes</hi> by prayer prevailed when yet his ſpirits and hands began to fail, and yet he prevailed more by prayer, then all the Hoaſt of Iſrael could do by their Arms, <hi>Exod:</hi> 17. 11, 12, 13, 14. and God commanded that this ſhould be written for a memorial. Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el you know how he wreſtled with God, and prevailed againſt his Brother <hi>Eſau,</hi> and four hundred armed men, <hi>Gen:</hi> 32. 28 for he had power with God, and with men, and prevailed: Little doth the world know what they do, when they ſet themſelves againſt ſuch praying Saints, their weapons of War are of no uſe here.</p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:118828:19"/>
               <p>3ly. The Saints have a chamber of <hi>Church communion,</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of you may read, Cant: 3. 4. <hi>I held him and would not let him go til I had brought him into my Mothers Houſe and into the chamber of her that conceived me,</hi> and this chamber is a hiding place for Saints <hi>Pſal: 27 5. In the ſecret of his Tabernacle wil he hide me, he wil ſet me upon a Rock.</hi> 4ly. God himſelf is as a chamber of ſafety to his people, where they may hide themſelves in time of fear and danger, <hi>Pſal: 119 114 Thou art my hiding place, and my ſhield; Pſal: 31. 20. Thou ſhalt hide them in the ſecret of thy preſence from the pride of man; thou ſhalt keep them ſecretly in a pavillion from the ſtrife of tongues:</hi> Lo! here is your ſafety Chriſtians. God wil keep you as the apple of his eye, &amp; what can the arm of fleſh do againſt the Almighty power of God.</p>
               <p>And laſt of all, let me add one word of comfort to you that now weep, for <hi>ye ſhall laugh,</hi> Luk: 6. 21. <hi>You now go forth weeping, bearing pretious ſeed, or ſeed of the Basket, but you ſhal doubtleſs come again with rejoycing bringing your ſheaves, you ſow in tears, but you ſhal reap in joy.</hi> Pſal: 126. 5. 6. You are impriſoned and hated for the ſake of Chriſt, but he wil (ſhortly) appear to your joy, and your adverſaries ſhal be aſhamed, <hi>Iſa:</hi> 66: 5. You hope for, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, and pray for the coming of Chriſt to rule over the world in righteouſneſs. Behold <hi>it is but a little while, and he that ſhall come will come, and wil not tarry: Heb:</hi> 10. 37: You are now un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derlings to the world, and now you ſuffer for Chriſt, but you ſhal reign as Kings upon Earth, <hi>Revel:</hi> 5: 10. Read the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon of the fifth Monarchy preached by Mr. <hi>Thomas Goodwyn,</hi> and printed by <hi>Livewel Chapman</hi> in <hi>Popeshead-Ally. Only be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to keep your garments unſpotted of the world and hold faſt the word of Christs patience that no man take your crown; Rev:</hi> 3. 10: 11. And when you ſee nothing but fire and ſword devouring on every hand, and the powers of Heaven ſhaken, and mens harts fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them for fear, and for looking after thoſe things which are coming on the earth: Then lift up your heads, for your redemption draweth nigh.</p>
               <p>Finally, to conclude, let me ſpeak a word or two to my Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren in <hi>New England.</hi> I know you are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot the Land of which this <hi>Prophet</hi> ſpeaks in particular, yet I may analogically ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:118828:20"/> the ſame to you: I could ſhew you how you have paſſed under two of theſe forms of Government in ſome meaſure and degree, how ſometimes you were under FEAR leſt the Magiſtrate ſhould have aſſumed too much power to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, (although it was more your fear then any reality) and you took a ſpeedy courſe to prevent that: and now you are fallen into the <hi>PIT,</hi> and have the main power reſiding in your Deputier. Beware leſt you come to another change of your own deviſing, for that will certainly become a SNARE. To you therefore give me leave to commend this word of advice and counſel as from God, that you may avoid the <hi>SNARE.</hi> Remember you had an old Prophet of the Lord a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you who is now at reſt, and he, according to the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom given him of God collected a whole Siſtemee, or body of Laws (as you cal it) out of the word of God: with a divine ſtamp upon them, and preſented the ſame to your general Court to have been ratified by their profeſſed ſubjection ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, which had you done, it might have ſaved you many thouſands of pounds that ſince have been ſpent in making, and repealing of Laws of your own framing, wheras as <hi>Chriſts</hi> Laws are made to your hand, &amp; are unrepealable. I know you wil acknowledg your own Laws are not perfect (ſome capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals only excepted, wherein you followed the advice of that antient Prophet) and you wil alſo acknowledg that there is no imperfection in the Laws given by <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> our King.</p>
               <p>Therfore I beſeech you again to reviſe what was commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to you by that faithful ſervant of Chriſt (Mr: <hi>Cotton</hi> I mean) and weigh with your ſelves whether Chriſts Laws be not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually as wiſe, compleat and perfect touching the civil admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrations of Judgment and Juſtice in the Common-wealth, as in the matters that concern his Church; and if ſo, then be perſwaded in the Lord to take his Laws for yours, and make them your <hi>Magna charta.</hi> And let all your adminiſtrations of Judgment be according to that perfect platform only: that it may be ſaid of your Judgments, they are not yours, but the Lords. I might give you ſundry arguments, and motives here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto; as firſt, from the example of that Nation whereof the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:118828:20"/> Prophet here ſpeaks, which after tryal of ſundry forms of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment finds nothing but FEAR, and a PIT, and a SNARE in them all: 2ly: Your ſolemn Ingagement before God in your Church covenants, to ſubmit your ſelves wholly to Jeſus Chriſt as your King; and the dangerous conſequences which wil follow the breach of that everlaſting covenant in ſo main a part of it. But 3ly: and principally let me preſs this argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as moſt ſuitable for Evangelical chriſtians: You wil here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by greatly honour the Lord Jeſus your King, when you own his wiſdom, faithfulneſs, and perfection as wel in civils as in ſpirituals. And you wil hereby become exemplary to all other chriſtian Nations whoſe eys are upon your actings.</p>
               <p>And let me tel you this, that your deſert herein hath great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly impeded the work of Chriſt with us. For wel may men rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon <hi>a minori ad majus;</hi> that if the Laws of Chriſt our King be not ſufficient to guide a ſmal colonie, much leſs can they be thought an <hi>adaequate rule</hi> for adminiſtration of Judgment and Juſtice in ſuch great and populous Nations: I might have ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded much more, but <hi>verba ſapienti ſat est.</hi> I could have anſwered many Objections, which are uſually made by ſuch as would graſp into their hands a ſhare with Chriſt in making Laws, but I judg it not fit for this place and this time: And I know you have many amongſt your ſelves that are far better able to obviate ſuch ſlight pretences &amp; ſhadows, theſe things I thought it my duty to recommend to you as one that hath ſpent upwards of 22 years amongſt you, and ſtil cordially af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects the peace of your <hi>Jeruſalem:</hi> I may aſſure you of this, that if old <hi>England</hi> Chriſtians who walk in holy fellowſhip toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had had the opportunity which you have had, and ſtill have, they would ere this have ſet up Jeſus Chriſt as King, not only in their churches but in the common-wealth alſo: You are a as a Beacon ſet on a Hil. Great things God hath done for you, and great things he expects from you: Do not you therfore ſo unkindly requite him as to diſhonour his Son by withdrawing your necks from under his Yoak, <hi>whoſe Yoak is eaſie, and his burden light:</hi> And the Lord that perſwades <hi>Japhet,</hi> perſwade you the Sons of <hi>Japhet</hi> to dwel in the Tents of <hi>Shem<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
